Guide to the John P. Robin Papers, 1943-2000 AIS.1977.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
John P. Robin Papers
1943-2000
1963-1994
ULS Archives & Special Collections
AIS.1977.06
87 boxes (87 boxes)
add
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Biography/History
John P. Robin, son of Peter and Bessie Robin, was born in Passavant Hospital in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, on October 15, 1912. Robin spent his infancy in the coal mining town of McDonald, Washington County, Pennsylvania, located approximately 20 miles southwest of downtown Pittsburgh. When Robin was three years old his parents moved the family to Pittsburgh and opened a pharmacy at Melwood Street and Centre Avenue in Oakland.
As a student, Robin attended Pittsburgh public schools, eventually graduating from Schenley high school before enrolling to the University of Pittsburgh where he majored in biology. Because of the Great Depression, Robin left school during his senior year prior to graduating. In 1934, Robin secured a job with the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette as a writer; however, his time at the Post-Gazette ended in 1936 when Robin entered into local politics. In November, 1936, Robin went to work as the secretary for Pittsburgh Mayor Cornelius D. Scully. Robin held that position until 1941 when the Mayor Scully appointed him Director of Welfare Activities in the city's Department of Welfare. Robin temporarily left his political career during World War II when he enlisted in the Army, serving from 1943-1945. Upon release from the Army, Robin returned to his hometown of Pittsburgh where in 1946 he was offered the position of Executive Secretary to Mayor David L. Lawrence. That same year the Urban Redevelopment Authority (URA) was formed and Robin selected as its first director. Robin would remain Executive Secretary and close confidant to Mayor Lawrence, as well as, serving at the director of the URA. As director, Robin oversaw the development of projects, such as Gateway Center and Point State Park, during Renaissance I. During a nine month stretch in 1955, Robin left Pittsburgh for Harrisburg to join Governor George M. Leader's cabinet as Secretary of Commerce. Robin returned to Pittsburgh in 1957 as president of the Regional Industrial Development Corporation (RIDC). Later that same year, Robin moved to Philadelphia where he served as the Executive Vice President of the Old Philadelphia Development Corporation. While there, Robin oversaw the redevelopment of Society Hill and Independence Mall. In 1963, Robin went to work for the Ford Foundation which relocated him to Calcutta, India. In Calcutta, Robin served as the chief consultant to the Calcutta Metropolitan Planning Organization. In 1967, Robin transferred to Nairobi, Kenya, where he spent three years directing Ford Foundation programs in nine East African Countries. From Nairobi, Robin went on to Athens, Greece, where he worked on a worldwide study of the free world's developing urban centers. In 1973, Robin returned to Pittsburgh as a Professor at the University of Pittsburgh and an advisor to the Allegheny Conference on Community Development. He served as the chairman of the URA board from 1977 to 1994 during Renaissance II while also serving as chairman of the Port Authority. Robin also served as the chairman of the Port Authority Special Task Force, vice chairman of the Allegheny County Planning Commission, county representative of the Southwestern Pennsylvania Regional Planning Commission, the Mayor's Oakland Task Force, and the Mayor's Development Council. John P. Robin died on May 07, 2000, at age 87.
Previous Citation
John P. Robin Papers, 1943-2000, AIS.1977.06, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
- The Academy for Contemporary Problems, 1972-2000; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains documents pertaining to the economics and future of American cities, and specific regions within the United States. In addition, there is Academy for Contemporary Problems news releases, meeting minutes and agendas, newspaper articles, and professional correspondence documents. There are also documents that specifically pertain to conferences such as the Aspen, Regional Growth Problems in U.S., and the Ohio River-Great Lakes conferences. This series contains documents primarily pertaining to Allegheny County covering topics such as road needs, the neighborhood preservation program, education and teachers, and the Glassport, Bridgeville, Forest Hills, Crafton, and Verona redevelopment projects. In addition, there are Allegheny County Planning Commission meeting minutes and agendas, budgets, multi-year plans/programs, newspaper articles, and professional correspondence documents. There are also airport advisory committee reports, airport zoning committee minutes, and airport southern expressway documents.
  - Report of the Panel on Title VII New Communities Program, The Future of the Industrial Midwest, Regional Institutes for Improving the Public Utilization of Technology, Professional correspondence; Bound reports regarding – Revitalizing Central City Investment, The Impact of Inflation of State and Local Government, Revitalizing the Northeastern Economy, Financial relief for trouble cities; Presentation folders containing – Policy Options for Neighborhood Empowerment, Multistate Institutions and Regional Growth Rural Development Issues, Newspaper articles; Loose documents pertaining to – Balanced Growth for the Northeast: Is it Possible?, News releases, Profession correspondence, Managing Urban Transition, The Demographic Future of the Cities of America, 1972-2000 (Box 56)
  - New Communities Legislation, Aspen Conference, Conference on Regional Growth Problem, Conference on Ohio River-Great Lakes, National Growth Policy; Bound reports regarding - Proposal for Designing an Economic Development Research Strategy for the Northeastern Region of the United States, Designing an Economic Development Strategy for the Great Lakes Region, The Academy for Contemporary Problems 1976 Annual Report, Financing of County Capital Improvements, A New Administration Mechanism for Allegheny County, The Pittsburgh Civic System: An Overview; Presentation folders containing – Future National Policies Concerning Urban Redevelopment; Loose documents pertaining to – Newspaper articles, Professional correspondence, various meeting agenda and minutes, 1972-1981 (Box 82)
- Allegheny County Planning Commission, 1966-1989; II.
  This series contains documents primarily pertaining to Allegheny County covering topics such as road needs, the neighborhood preservation program, education and teachers, and the Glassport, Bridgeville, Forest Hills, Crafton, and Verona redevelopment projects. In addition, there are Allegheny County Planning Commission meeting minutes and agendas, budgets, multi-year plans/programs, newspaper articles, and professional correspondence documents. There are also airport advisory committee reports, airport zoning committee minutes, and airport southern expressway documents.
  - Bound reports regarding – Allegheny County Road Needs Study, Capital Monitoring System Updated report, Subdivision Regulations, Allegheny County Neighborhood Preservation Program, Housing in Allegheny County; Loose documents pertaining to – Port Authority Regular meeting of the Board minutes, Professional Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 4)
  - Bound report regarding – Capital Improvement Budget; Loose documents pertaining to – Profession correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 5)
  - Armstrong County Planning Commission Data Resource Manual, Aero-Notes, Allegheny County Planning Commission – Search committee, Airport Zoning Committee minutes, Community Development Act, Professional correspondence; Bound reports regarding – Development Sketch Plan for Armstrong County, Six Year Plan and 1978 Capital Budget, Rural Water Improvement Plan, Turtle Creek Watershed Erosion and Sedimentation Control Study; Loose documents pertaining to – Professional correspondence, meeting minutes, progress reports, 1973-1979 (Box 8)
  - Catalog of State Assistance to Allegheny County; bound reports regarding – 1978 Capital Budget Year End Summary report, Capital Improvements Budget (1975-1976), Capital Improvements Program, Capital improvements progress Report, Preapplication for Feasibility Study for an Energy/Resource Recovery Facility; Loose documents pertaining to meeting agenda and minutes, Profession correspondence, 1975-1981 (Box 21)
  - Allegheny County Planning Commission – Meeting agenda and minutes; Bound reports regarding – 1981 Financial Report Summary, Six Year Capital Development Program, Marina Study, Planning Department Annual Report, Borough of Homestead Redevelopment Area Basic Condition Report, Proposed Redevelopment Area of Borough of Braddock; Loose documents pertaining to – meeting agenda ad minutes, Professional correspondence, 1981-1989 (Box 29)
  - Various documents concerning – Southwestern PA Regional Planning Commission; Bound reports regarding - Transportation Improvement Program for SPRPC Region, Pitcairn Rail Yards Redevelopment Area: Basic Conditions Report, The First Two Years: The Public Education Fund, Mini-Grants for Teachers, Partners in Education, Allegheny County Capital Budget Report, Allegheny Conference on Community Development Report, Port Authority of Allegheny County Annual Report; Loose documents pertaining to – various meeting agendas and minutes, Professional correspondence, newspaper articles, Progress reports, 1977-1987 (Box 33)
  - Block Grant Program, Allegheny County Planning Commission meeting agenda and minutes, Professional Correspondence; Bound reports regarding - The Pennsylvania Energy Primer, Report on Existing Condition Proposed Glassport Redevelopment Area, Allegheny County Grantee Performance Report, Report on Existing Conditions Proposed Bridgeville Redevelopment Area, Proposed Forest Hills Redevelopment Project, Proposed Verona Redevelopment Project, Housing Programs in Allegheny County, Subdivision Regulations; Loose documents pertaining to – Meeting agenda and minutes, Newspaper articles, Professional correspondence, 1979-1982 (Box 47)
  - Bound reports regarding - Planning for Allegheny County, Pacesetter Report, Report on Existing Conditions: Proposed Crafton Redevelopment Area, Allegheny County Grantee Performance Report, Allegheny County Comprehensive Community Energy Management Action Plan, Water and Wastewater Residue Management Study, Certification of Blight: Braddock Borough, Allegheny County Subdivision and Land Development Regulations, Certification of Blight: Dormont Borough, Final Report and Proposed Home Rule Charter, Allegheny County Proposed Land Use Plan, Verona Redevelopment Project; Loose documents pertaining to – various meeting agendas and minutes, Newspaper articles, Professional correspondence, Proposed projects, Energy Audit, 1966-1986 (Box 85)
- Citizens Task Force on Refuse Disposal, 1972-1981; III.
  This series contains documents pertaining to solid waste and includes reports, articles, and resolutions on solid waste disposal. In addition, there are Citizens Task Force on Refuse Disposal meeting minutes and agendas, newspaper articles, Allegheny County Sanitary Authority annual reports, and professional correspondence documents.
  - Various articles, reports, and resolutions; Professional correspondence, newspaper articles, Waste Age Magazine; Bound reports regarding – How Shall We Collect the Garbage?, Hidden Waste: Potential for Energy Conservation, Proposed Solid Waste Processing and Resource Recovery; Loose documents pertaining to – various documents and professional correspondence, 1972-1981 (Box 87)
- The Ford Foundation, 1947-2000; IV.
  This series contains multiple volumes of the Ford Foundation Letter, annual reports, professional correspondence documents, newspaper articles, various versions of a comprehensive report Robin was involved in preparing concerning urban revitalization in foreign countries, and various papers authored by Robin. In addition, there are documents pertaining to topics, such as urban redevelopment programs, in several countries including Nigeria, Kenya, Argentina, Venezuela, Columbia, Mexico, Pakistan, Peru, Chili, Brazil, Panama, Philippines, Tanzania, Malaysia, Singapore, Turkey, Thailand, Uganda, Zambia, Ghana, India, Calcutta, Bombay, and Lebanon.
  - News releases, Ford Foundation Letters, Bound reports regarding – Four Foundation annual reports, A Decent Place to Live, About the Ford Foundation, Current Comment of the Ford Foundation, 1963-1973 (Box 13-B)
  - Final Report 1972 –draft and scrap notes; Professional correspondence, The Next Decade: Recommendations for the Ford Foundation-Vol. I:Part II, Various documents concerning Nigeria, Nairobi, and Kenya – Annual reports, maps, professional correspondence, newspaper and journal articles, and bound reports, 1966-1973 (Box 14)
  - Professional correspondence, Ford working paper, Final report – first draft, working paper, Discussion papers I, II, and III; Papers and Memos brought back from Delhi, Bound reports regarding – International Urbanization Survey: Final Report, A Survey of Regional Planning Research Activities in Western Europe and Yugoslavia, The Next Decade: Recommendations for the Ford Foundation, Infrastructure Problems of the Cities of Developing Countries, 1971-1972 (Box 15)
  - Survey of North American Programs, Working draft and original final concerning Argentina; Various documents concerning – Teaching, Research, and Higher Education, and Educational Assistance for Developing Countries; Working draft concerning Venezuela; 1969 Annual Report, Proposed Structure of the Regional Centre for Urban problems and Planning, The Impact of The University of Pittsburgh on the Local Economy, Newsletter, Belgrade Rapid Transit Study Design Report, professional correspondence; Bound reports regarding – Spatial Policies for Regional Development, the Ford Foundation, 1969-1973 (Box 16)
  - Various documents concerning - Mexico, Columbia, Chile, Brazil, Peru, and Pakistan, 1966-2000 (Box 17)
  - Planning and Development Collaborative International – Information and Quarterly Newsletter; Various documents concerning - Pakistan, Institute of Business Administration: University of Dacca, and the Philippines, 1963-1972 (Box 35)
  - Plans and Policies for Karachi, Physical Planning and housing Section of the National Planning Commission, Welfare Aspects of National Policy Toward City Sizes, Changing Relations Between Urban and Rural Areas in the Economic Development of Mexico, Fellowship Programs in Natural resources and Urban Economics; Papers authored by Mr. Robin – The Shaping f the Urban World, Robert Pease interview, Urban Research: Usage and Abuse, The Complicators and the Simplifiers: Do We Really Have an Urban Crisis; Bound reports, 1960-1974 (Box 36)
  - Various documents concerning – Tanzania, Malaysia, Singapore, Dakar, Turkey, Thailand; Papers and Talks – Problems of a Growing Population, Education and Social Values, The Quality of Urban Life with Special Reference to Developing Countries; Bound Reports, 1967-1972 (Box 37)
  - Various documents concerning – Uganda and East Pakistan, World Health Organization (W.H.O.), Centre for Housing & Development U.N., Bound reports regarding – Uganda and Nigeria; Loose documents pertaining to – Inter-Regional Seminar on Improvements of Slums and Uncontrolled Settlements, 1966-1973 (Box 38)
  - Various documents concerning – Uganda and Pakistan, U.N., UNESCO, UNICEF; Bound reports, 1957-1972 (Box 39)
  - Miscellaneous documents on U.S., New York, and Pennsylvania; Agriculture, U.S. Foreign Assistance, AID, HUD, Inter-Agency Consolidated report Latin America/Caribbean Region; Bound reports regarding – Latin America, Ghana, Ethiopia, Outdoor Recreation for America, Delaware River Basin report, Publically Provided and Assisted Housing in the U.S.A., The Nature, Impact, and Prosecution pf White Collar Crime; Loose documents pertaining to – Department of State, Agency for International Development reports, A Housing program for Latin America, 1960-1976 (Box 40)
  - Various documents concerning – Zambia, Venezuela, Latin America, and Wayne State; Bound Reports regarding - Zambia, Belgrade, Malaysia; Presentation folder contain – The Food Crisis, Food: Means of Life, Newspaper articles, 1965-1975 (Box 41)
  - Various documents concerning – Zambia; Bound reports regarding – Nigeria, Pakistan, WHO, The Coming Urban Crisis in Asia, 1969-1975 (Box 42)
  - Various documents concerning – Brazil, Latin America, South East Asia, East Africa, Egypt; Plan of Operation for Urbanization Study, Papers on Planning, Professional Correspondence, Newspaper articles; Bound reports regarding – India, 1960-1972 (Box 48)
  - Various documents concerning – Ghana, Kenya, Tanzania, Nigeria, Zambia, Pakistan, Indonesia, Thailand, Columbia, Venezuela; Ford Complied documents, Urbanization Survey, Update to Travel and Study manual, Grant Proposals, Bound reports regarding – Management and Program Trends in the Fifties and Sixties, The Foundation and the Less Developed Countries the Decade of the Seventies, Overseas Development Self-Study of the India Program, Lima Field Office Annual Report, 1947-1973 (Box 49)
  - Various documents concerning – Africa, India, South East Asia, Stockholm; Conference on Urbanization, Environment, Employment in Less Developed Countries; Bound reports regarding – The Foundation's Work on Population, reports in foreign languages,; Presentation folder containing – information on the Foundation for Cooperative housing, 1956-1972 (Box 50)
  - Planning School Kumasi, Ghana: Team report, Bound reports regarding – Ghana, Jamaica, Peru, Chile, Race and the Third World, International Urbanization Survey Findings and Recommendations, 1967-1970 (Box 51)
  - Various documents concerning – India, Kenya, Nairobi, Columbia, Venezuela, Latin America; Professional correspondence; Bound reports regarding – Nairobi, Kenya, Draft Programme and Budget (1970-1971), Site and Service Schemes, 1964-1972 (Box 52)
  - Various documents concerning – India, Indonesia; Papers on Inter-American Development Bank; Bound reports regarding – India, Tanzania, Latin America, 1958-1989 (Box 53)
  - Various documents concerning – Lebanon, Beirut, Madagascar, Malaysia, Morocco, Mexico; Bound reports regarding – Mexico, Malaysia, 1966-1972 (Box 54)
  - Various documents concerning – Nigeria, Latin America; National Academy of Science, The National Urban Coalition 1973 Budget, Papers and Conferences sponsored by O.A.S. on Urban Development; Bound reports regarding – Nigeria, Prospects of the World Food Supply, 1966-1973 (Box 55)
  - Terzo working papers, Talking Points: Rosser – draft reports and memos, working notes, professional correspondence, Various documents concerning – Calcutta; Bound reports regarding – South Africa, International Urbanization Survey: Findings and Recommendations, Ekistics magazine; Loose documents pertaining to – East Africa, The Political Implications of Demographic Change in Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Urban Research: Usage and Abuse, 1969-1989 (Box 61)
- Pittsburgh City Planning Commission, 1971-1997; V.
  This series contains documents such as Planning Commission meeting minutes and agendas, budgets, multi-year plans/programs, and professional correspondence documents.
  - Pittsburgh City Planning Commission agendas and minutes; Bound reports regarding – Pittsburgh Budget 1979, Housing Authority Annual Report; Loose documents pertaining to – Pittsburgh City Planning Commission addenda and minutes, 1977-1981 (Box 58)
  - Allegheny County Planning Commission agenda and minutes, Pittsburgh City Planning Commission agenda and minutes; Bound reports regarding Draft Six Year Development Program and 1993 Capital Budget; Loose documents pertaining to – Professional Correspondence, 1989-1993 (Box 75)
  - Pittsburgh City Planning Commission agendas and minutes, Allegheny County Planning Commission agenda, minutes, and Six Year Capital Development Programs; Bound reports regarding – Progress in the Neighborhoods: 1983-1988, City of Pittsburgh Six Year Development Programs, 1983-1997 (Box 76)
  - Loose documents pertaining to – Pittsburgh City Planning Commission agenda and minutes, 1981-1986 (Box 84)
- Port Authority of Allegheny County, 1970-1993; VI.
  This series contains Port Authority board packets for both regular meeting and special meeting which contain minutes and agendas. There are staff reports to the board, newspaper articles, PA Transit News publications, professional correspondence documents, proposed operating budgets, monthly financial reports, Port Authority resolutions, Audit and Finance Committee meeting minutes, Consumer Relations Committee meeting minutes, PAT's People Flyer publications, letters from the public, strategic plans, and Planning and Construction Committee minutes and agendas. In addition, there are documents pertaining to specific projects such as the East Busway Feasibility study, South Hills Alternative Analysis study, Commuter Rail, Mon Valley Transit study, Pittsburgh Light Rail, South Hills Light Rail, and airport busway.
  - Board membership, Port Authority newspaper articles, South Hills alternative analysis study, Professional correspondence; Bound reports regarding – Board meeting reports, Population estimates (1975), Proposed operating budget (1976); Loose documents pertaining to – Transit in Toronto, Mass Transit Canada, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
    Box 1 includes: Board Membership, 1973-1974, P.R., 1973-1975, Newspaper Articles, PA Transit News Articles, South Hills Alternative Analysis Study, Professional Correspondence, Bound Reports (35), 1975-1976, Regular Meeting of the Board, Special Meeting of the Board, Staff Report to the Board, 1975 Population Estimates, East Busway Feasibility Study, Proposed Operating Budget, 1976, Transit in Toronto, and Mass Transit Canada
  - Transportation Task Force professional correspondence, Transportation Task Force Technical Committee meeting minutes, Transportation Task Force consultant applications professional correspondence, South Hills Corridor transit alternative evaluation, Supplemental Memorandum on Early Action Program; Bound reports regarding – Reports on Workmen Compensation Dilemma, South Hills Corridor transit alternative evaluation, 1973-1976 (Box 2)
    Box 2 includes: Transportation Task Force, 1975-1976, Professional Correspondence, Technical Committee, 1975, Meeting Minutes, Consultant Applications 1975, South Hills Corridor Transit Alternatives Evaluation, Minutes 1973-1975, Supplemental Memorandum on Early Action Program, Bound Reports (9) 1974-1976, Report on Workmen's Compensation Dilemma, South Hills Corridor Alternatives Evaluation, Port Authority Regular Meeting of the Board, publications-1975-1976, and Meeting Minutes.
  - Bound reports regarding – Proposed operating budget, PAT Staff report to the board, PAT regular meeting to the board, Commuter rail potential, Audit report, 1973-1976 (Box 3)
  - Bound reports regarding – Port Authority Monthly financial reports, Port Authority Staff report to the board, Port Authority regular meeting of the board, PAT Quarterly progress report, South Hills Corridor transit alternative evaluation, Port of Pittsburgh fact finder; Loose documents pertaining to – Professional correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper articles, Transportation ask Force minutes; Bound reports regarding –Port Authority Monthly financial reports, Port Authority Regular meeting of the board, Port Authority Staff report to the board, Port Authority Quarterly progress report, American Public Transit Association Journals; Loose documents pertaining to- Professional correspondence, Newspaper articles, 1970-1977 (Box 7)